Many people ask us
which is the best health insurance policy?
So today we will compare two top policies in the Policy Analyzer series.
These top
policies in terms of insurers, in terms
of features and in terms of claims
experience.  These are two policies.
HDFCO Optima Secure Plus on one side and
ICICI LB Elevate on the other side.  We will do an in-depth comparison of both these policies
with all the features
and tell you which policy you should choose.
Before we start, please like my video
and subscribe
to my channel so that we can keep sharing such interesting
insights with you.
Point number one is room rent limit.  If we
talk about HDFCO Optima Secure PS, there
is no room rent limit in this policy.  You can add a rider to the policy to add a room rent limit.  There is
no room rent limit in the but base policy.  If
you talk about ICICI Low LBA Elevate, then the
room rent limit for a single private AC room is included in the base policy.  But you can
add a room modifier to make it no room rent
limit.  So broadly speaking, there is
no room rent limit in both the policies.
Point number two is copay and deductible.   There is
no copayment in both the policies.  Voluntary option of deductible is available in HDFC and Optima Sure Plu.   If
you want, you can enter a deductible of Rs 25,000, 500, or up to Rs 1 lakh.  In
front of which you
get premium discount.  Whereas the
deductible option is not available in ICICI LBD Elevate.
So if we look at the copay and deductible,
HDFC Ago Optima Sure P has a
big advantage in that they have a deductible
available and you
can reduce your premium by using it.  Point
number three consumable cover.
Consumable cover is available in both the policies.
In HDFCO Optima Secure Plus, this
consumable cover is inbuilt in the policy.  You
can remove it through a rider.
Consumable cover
is available through a rider in ICICI Low LBAD Elevate.  You need to
add Claim Protector, a rider, to
cover consumables.  Point
number four restoration benefit.  The
restoration benefit is unlimited in both the policies.  There are no
conditions on restoration benefit in both the policies.
Same person,
same illness, same person, different illness.  Everything
is covered under the policies.  ICICI LBD
Elevate earlier had a waiting period of 45 days.
Same person for same illness.  Now it has been
removed.  This means that the
restoration benefit in both the policies
is unlimited without any questions being asked.
Point number four bonus.  Both the policies
offer very different types of bonuses.
First we come to HDFCO Optima Secure PS, in that
if you buy a policy of 10 lakhs
then it becomes 20 lakhs from day one
and it adds 10 lakhs every year year after year.
So for example, in the fifth year
he will add a bonus of Rs 50 lakh.  In the 10th year
he will add one year bonus and so on.
This bonus will keep getting added whether you claim it or not.
So in ICICI NBAD Elevate you will
get a bonus of Rs 12 lakh in the first year.
Whereas in HDFCGO Optima Secure PS you will
get a bonus of Rs 20 lakh in the first year.   This
is the USP or biggest benefit of both the policies.  Both the policies will add Rs 10 lakh every year
for an unlimited number of years in a Rs 10 lakh policy.
This
protects you from medical inflation.  Medical inflation in India is
around 14%.  So you are combating 14% medical
inflation.
By adding 100% sum insured, you get thumbs up for the
bonus of both the policies and this
is a very crucial feature of your policy.  Now let's come to
pre and post hospitalization cover.  HDFCO
Optima Secure Plus offers cover for 60 days pre-
hospitalization and 180 days post-
hospitalization.  Whereas ICICI Low
LBA Elevate has a cover of 90 days pre-hospitalization
and 180 days post-hospitalization.
So in this the cover of ICICI Low LBA
is very good.  Pre and post
hospitalization means
doctor costs,
medicines and tests before your hospitalization and
these three things are covered even after hospitalization.
So the pre-occupation cover is slightly higher in ICICI Low LBA.
Whereas in HDFC Ergo Optima
Secure it is only for 60 days.  Now let us come to
all the limits on treatment of diseases.
Both these policies are top-notch comprehensive
policies.  There is
no sublimit on the treatment of any disease.  All
diseases are covered up to the sum insured.  Now let us come to the
waiting period for pre-existing medical conditions.
In both the policies, if you
come with any pre-existing medical condition,
then there is a waiting period of 3 years on that.
Day one coverage is available for four illnesses.
Asthma, blood pressure, diabetes,
cholesterol.  Day one coverage is available for these four diseases
in both the policies.
Apart from this, day
one coverage is not available for any disease.  There will be a
waiting period of 3 years for all other diseases.
Now let's talk about an extra feature
called Unlimited Tay.  In both
HDFC Ago Optima Sure P and ICICI Lombard
Elevate, if you add a rider,
you get an unlimited claim during the lifetime of the policy.
This
is available in both the policies.  In HDFC Ago Optima Sure Plus
it is called Limitless Rider and
in ICICI LBD Elevate it is called Infinite Care.
Now let's talk about premium discounts.
In HDFC Ago Optima Sure P,
if you are below 35 years of age, you
get a lifetime discount of 5%.  Apart
from this, if you do not make any claim under the policy
in a year, the company gives you up to 21%
discount.  If we
talk about discounts on ICICI LBA Elevate, then
up to 15% discount is available on ICICI LBD Elevate
based on your credit score.
If your credit score is
better than 700, you
get up to 15% discount on premium.  Now let's talk about
eligibility.  Who
is eligible for which policy?  In HDFC Ago Optima Sure
PS, you are eligible for the age group of 18 to 60 years.
You cannot take this policy after 60 years old.
If you want to
take a policy after 60 years of age, then you will have to
go to the old Optima Secure.  If you
talk about ICICI LBAT Elevate, there
is no such cap here.  Everyone between 18 to 99 years
old can apply for this policy.
Now let's talk about maternity.
Maternity cover up
to 2 lakhs is available in both these policies.  There
is a waiting period of 2 years for maternity in both the policies.
But according to us,
both these insurances increase the premium for maternity.
According to us,
maternity does not make any sense in both the policies
and it would be
better if you do not take maternity in both the policies.  Now
talking about the hospital network, the
hospital network of both the insurers
is quite extensive.  12 to 14,000 hospitals
covered for both insurances.  Now if we
talk about the premium, if we look at the
premium of 10 lakh for a 30 year old in Mumbai zone, then the
premium of HDFC Ago Optima Sure P comes around 14,000.  Similarly, the
premium for ICICI LMB comes to ₹12,000.  The
premium of HDFC Ago Optima Sure P
is Rs 14,000 because if you take a policy of Rs 10 lakh,
it becomes Rs 20 lakh from day one.
So net net it is Rs 20, if you
compare it with ICICI LB then almost
about the premium is the same for both the policies.
So now we have comprehensively
looked at the features of both the policies.  Nearly the
features of both the policies are quite same
and similar.  So how
should you decide which policy to
choose?  According to us, both the
insurers are quite good.  The
claim settlements of both the insurances are also very
good and our experience
with both the insurers has been excellent in the last 10 years.  According to
us, the number
one thing you can do is
check the hospital network of both the insurers.  You should definitely go with the policy of the insurer whose
hospital network is
very good in your area.   Keep in mind that
we always
try to take cashless claims in insurance.  There is
never any problem in cashless claims.
So for this, give preference to the insurance whose
hospital network list is very good in your area.
Point number two, if you
are above 60 years old then you have to directly
go towards ICICI Lombard Elevate.
Because ICICI LMB is available at high rates.  Whereas
that product is not available with HDFC Ago.
Point number three, if you are below 35
then according to us you
should go for HDFC Ago Optima Sure P because
it is giving you attractive discounts
which ICICI LBD Elevate is not giving.
Now finally, if you are between 18 to 60
then your medical conditions will decide whether
you will go for ICICI LB Elevate or
HDFC Argo Optima Secure.
For example, if you have a knee replacement
line up.  We don't think you will
find a policy in ICICI LB Elevate.  You will have to
stick to HDFC Ago Optima Sure only.
So according to us, on a case by case
basis, you should see whether you want to
buy HDFC Algo Optima Sure P or ICICI LBAT
Elevate.  Both the policies are very top
notch and you should consider both the policies.
Next time you are
buying a health insurance policy.   Let
us know in the comments section which policy we should compare next.
We will compare those policies after taking your feedback.  Stay
with us for more such
interesting insights and deep
analysis on health insurance, life
insurance and personal finance.